<?xml version="1.0"?>
<LinuxManPage>
<!-- 	User Command - cmp-->
	<page id = "cmp">
		<Type>User</Type>
		<Name>  cmp </Name>
		<Usage> cmp -- compare two files byte by byte
			cmp [OPTION]... FILE1 [FILE2 [SKIP1 [SKIP2]]]
		</Usage>
		<Description> Compare two files byte by byte.

			The optional SKIP1 and SKIP2 specify the number of bytes to skip
			at the beginning of each file (zero by default).

			Mandatory arguments to long options are mandatory for short
			options too.

			-b, --print-bytes
			      print differing bytes

			-i, --ignore-initial=SKIP
			      skip first SKIP bytes of both inputs

			-i, --ignore-initial=SKIP1:SKIP2
			      skip first SKIP1 bytes of FILE1 and first SKIP2 bytes of FILE2

			-l, --verbose
			      output byte numbers and differing byte values

			-n, --bytes=LIMIT
			      compare at most LIMIT bytes

			-s, --quiet, --silent
			      suppress all normal output

			--help display this help and exit

			-v, --version
			      output version information and exit

			SKIP values may be followed by the following multiplicative suffixes:
			kB 1000, K 1024, MB 1,000,000, M 1,048,576, GB 1,000,000,000, G
			1,073,741,824, and so on for T, P, E, Z, Y.

			If a FILE is '-' or missing, read standard input.  Exit status is 0
			if inputs are the same, 1 if different, 2 if trouble.		
	   	</Description>
		<OtherReferences> Copyright © 2012 Thomas Leonard. You may redistribute copies
			of this program under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
			License.
		</OtherReferences>
	</page>
	<!-- System Calls - chmod -->
	<page id = "chmod">
		<Type>System</Type>
		<Name>  chmod </Name>
		<Usage> chmod -- change file modes or Access Control Lists
			chmod [-fv] [-R [-H | -L | -P]] mode file ...
			chmod [-fv] [-R [-H | -L | -P]] [-a | +a | =a] ACE file ...
			chmod [-fhv] [-R [-H | -L | -P]] [-E] file ...
			chmod [-fhv] [-R [-H | -L | -P]] [-C] file ...
			chmod [-fhv] [-R [-H | -L | -P]] [-N] file ...
		</Usage>
		<Description> The chmod utility modifies the file mode bits of the listed files as
			specified by the mode operand. It may also be used to modify the
			Access.

			Control Lists (ACLs) associated with the listed files.

			The generic options are as follows:

			-f  Do not display a diagnostic message if chmod could not modify
				the mode for file.

			-H  If the -R option is specified, symbolic links on the command line
			 	are followed.  (Symbolic links encountered in the tree traversal
			 	are not followed by default.)

			-h  If the file is a symbolic link, change the mode of the link
			 	itself rather than the file that the link points to.

			-L  If the -R option is specified, all symbolic links are followed.

			-P  If the -R option is specified, no symbolic links are followed.
				This is the default.

			-R  Change the modes of the file hierarchies rooted in the files
			 	instead of just the files themselves.

			-v 	Cause chmod to be verbose, showing filenames as the mode is
				modified.  If the -v flag is specified more than once, the
				old and new modes of the file will also be printed, in both
				octal and symbolic notation.

			The -H, -L and -P options are ignored unless the -R option is
			specified. In addition, these options override each other and
			the command's actions are determined by the last one specified.

			Only the owner of a file or the super-user is permitted to change the
			mode of a file.

		</Description>
		<OtherReferences> chflags(1), fsaclctl(1), install(1), chmod(2), stat(2), umask(2),
			fts(3), setmode(3), symlink(7), chown(8), mount(8), sticky(8)
		</OtherReferences>
	</page>
	<!-- Library Functions - abort -->
	<page id = "abort">
		<Type>Library</Type>
		<Name>  abort</Name>
		<Usage> abort -- cause abnormal program termination
			#include stdlib.h

     		void
     		abort(void);
		</Usage>
		<Description> The abort() function causes abnormal program termination to occur,
			unless the signal SIGABRT is being caught and the signal handler
			does not return.

    		Any open streams are flushed and closed.
		</Description>
		<OtherReferences> sigaction(2), exit(3)
		</OtherReferences>
	</page>
	<!-- Devices - loop -->
	<page id = "loop">
		<Type>Devices</Type>

		<Name>  loop</Name>
		<Usage> loop, loop-control -- loop devices
			#include linux/loop.h
		</Usage>
		<Description> The loop device is a block device that maps its data blocks not to a
       		physical device such as a hard disk or optical disk drive, but to the
      		blocks of a regular file in a filesystem or to another block device.
       		This can be useful for example to provide a block device for a
       		filesystem image stored in a file, so that it can be mounted with the
       		mount(8) command.  You could do

              $ dd if=/dev/zero of=file.img bs=1MiB count=10
              $ sudo losetup /dev/loop4 file.img
              $ sudo mkfs -t ext4 /dev/loop4
              $ sudo mkdir /myloopdev
              $ sudo mount /dev/loop4 /myloopdev

       		See losetup(8) for another example.

       		A transfer function can be specified for each loop device for
       		encryption and decryption purposes.

       		The following ioctl(2) operations are provided by the loop block
       		device:

       		LOOP_SET_FD
              Associate the loop device with the open file whose file
              descriptor is passed as the (third) ioctl(2) argument.

       		LOOP_CLR_FD
              Disassociate the loop device from any file descriptor.

       		LOOP_SET_STATUS
              Set the status of the loop device using the (third) ioctl(2)
              argument.  This argument is a pointer to loop_info structure,
              defined in linux/loop.h as:

                  struct loop_info {
                      int           lo_number;            /* ioctl r/o */
                      dev_t         lo_device;            /* ioctl r/o */
                      unsigned long lo_inode;             /* ioctl r/o */
                      dev_t         lo_rdevice;           /* ioctl r/o */
                      int           lo_offset;
                      int           lo_encrypt_type;
                      int           lo_encrypt_key_size;  /* ioctl w/o */
                      int           lo_flags;             /* ioctl r/o */
                      char          lo_name[LO_NAME_SIZE];
                      unsigned char lo_encrypt_key[LO_KEY_SIZE];
                                                          /* ioctl w/o */
                      unsigned long lo_init[2];
                      char          reserved[4];
                  };

              The encryption type (lo_encrypt_type) should be one of
              LO_CRYPT_NONE, LO_CRYPT_XOR, LO_CRYPT_DES, LO_CRYPT_FISH2,
              LO_CRYPT_BLOW, LO_CRYPT_CAST128, LO_CRYPT_IDEA,
              LO_CRYPT_DUMMY, LO_CRYPT_SKIPJACK, or (since Linux 2.6.0)
              LO_CRYPT_CRYPTOAPI.

              The lo_flags field is a bit mask that can include zero or more
              of the following:

              LO_FLAGS_READ_ONLY
                     The loopback device is read-only.

              LO_FLAGS_AUTOCLEAR (since Linux 2.6.25)
                     The loopback device will autodestruct on last close.

              LO_FLAGS_PARTSCAN (since Linux 3.2)
                     Allow automatic partition scanning.

       		LOOP_GET_STATUS
              Get the status of the loop device.  The (third) ioctl(2)
              argument must be a pointer to a struct loop_info.

      		LOOP_CHANGE_FD (since Linux 2.6.5)
              Switch the backing store of the loop device to the new file
              identified file descriptor specified in the (third) ioctl(2)
              argument, which is an integer.  This operation is possible
              only if the loop device is read-only and the new backing store
              is the same size and type as the old backing store.

       		LOOP_SET_CAPACITY (since Linux 2.6.30)
              Resize a live loop device.  One can change the size of the
              underlying backing store and then use this operation so that
              the loop driver learns about the new size.  This operation
              takes no argument.

       		Since Linux 2.6, there are two new ioctl(2) operations:

       		LOOP_SET_STATUS64, LOOP_GET_STATUS64
              These are similar to LOOP_SET_STATUS and LOOP_GET_STATUS
              described above but use the loop_info64 structure, which has
              some additional fields and a larger range for some other
              fields:

                  struct loop_info64 {
                      uint64_t lo_device;                   /* ioctl r/o */
                      uint64_t lo_inode;                    /* ioctl r/o */
                      uint64_t lo_rdevice;                  /* ioctl r/o */
                      uint64_t lo_offset;
                      uint64_t lo_sizelimit;/* bytes, 0 == max available */
                      uint32_t lo_number;                   /* ioctl r/o */
                      uint32_t lo_encrypt_type;
                      uint32_t lo_encrypt_key_size;         /* ioctl w/o */
                      uint32_t lo_flags;                    /* ioctl r/o */
                      uint8_t  lo_file_name[LO_NAME_SIZE];
                      uint8_t  lo_crypt_name[LO_NAME_SIZE];
                      uint8_t  lo_encrypt_key[LO_KEY_SIZE]; /* ioctl w/o */
                      uint64_t lo_init[2];
                  };

   			/dev/loop-control
	      	
	      	Since Linux 3.1, the kernel provides the /dev/loop-control device,
	      	which permits an application to dynamically find a free device, and
	       	to add and remove loop devices from the system.  To perform these
	       	operations, one first opens /dev/loop-control and then employs one of
	       	the following ioctl(2) operations:

       		LOOP_CTL_GET_FREE
              Allocate or find a free loop device for use.  On success, the
              device number is returned as the result of the call.  This
              operation takes no argument.

       		LOOP_CTL_ADD
              Add the new loop device whose device number is specified as a
              long integer in the third ioctl(2) argument.  On success, the
              device index is returned as the result of the call.  If the
              device is already allocated, the call fails with the error
              EEXIST.

       		LOOP_CTL_REMOVE
              Remove the loop device whose device number is specified as a
              long integer in the third ioctl(2) argument.  On success, the
              device number is returned as the result of the call.  If the
              device is in use, the call fails with the error EBUSY.

		</Description>
		<OtherReferences> losetup(8), mount(8)
		</OtherReferences>
	</page>	

	<!-- Files - term	 -->
	<page id = "term">
		<Type>Files</Type>

		<Name>  term </Name>
		<Usage> term -- format of compiled term file.
			term
		</Usage>
		<Description> STORAGE LOCATION
       			Compiled terminfo descriptions are placed under the directory
       			@TERMINFO@.  Two configurations are supported (when building the
       			ncurses libraries):

	       		directory tree
	            	A two-level scheme is used to avoid a linear search of a huge
	            	UNIX system directory: @TERMINFO@/c/name where name is the
					name of the terminal, and c is the first character of name.
					Thus, act4 can be found in the file @TERMINFO@/a/act4.
					Synonyms for the same terminal are implemented by multiple
					links to the same compiled file.

	       		hashed database
		            Using Berkeley database, two types of records are stored: the
		            terminfo data in the same format as stored in a directory tree
		            with the terminfo's primary name as a key, and records
		            containing only aliases pointing to the primary name.

		            If built to write hashed databases, ncurses can still read
		            terminfo databases organized as a directory tree, but cannot
		            write entries into the directory tree.  It can write (or
		            rewrite) entries in the hashed database.

		            ncurses distinguishes the two cases in the TERMINFO and
		            TERMINFO_DIRS environment variable by assuming a directory tree
		            for entries that correspond to an existing directory, and hashed
		            database otherwise.

   			STORAGE FORMAT
				The format has been chosen so that it will be the same on all
				hardware.  An 8 or more bit byte is assumed, but no
				assumptions about byte ordering or sign extension are made.

				The compiled file is created with the @TIC@ program, and read by the
				routine setupterm.  The file is divided into six parts: the header,
				terminal names, boolean flags, numbers, strings, and string
				table.

				The header section begins the file.  This section contains six
				short integers in the format described below. These integers are:

				    (1) the magic number (octal 0432);

				    (2) the size, in bytes, of the names section;

				    (3) the number of bytes in the boolean section;

				    (4) the number of short integers in the numbers section;

				    (5) the number of offsets (short integers) in the strings
				    section;

				    (6) the size, in bytes, of the string table.

			Short integers are stored in two 8-bit bytes.  The first byte
			contains the least significant 8 bits of the value, and the second
			byte contains the most significant 8 bits.  (Thus, the value
			represented is 256*second+first.)  The value -1 is represented
			by the two bytes 0377, 0377; other negative values are illegal.
			This value generally means that the corresponding capability is
			missing from this terminal.  Note that this format corresponds
			to the hardware of the VAX and PDP-11 (that is, little-endian
			machines). Machines where this does not correspond to the hardware
			must read the integers as two bytes and compute the little-endian
			value.

			The terminal names section comes next.  It contains the first line
			of the terminfo description, listing the various names for the
			terminal, separated by the `|' character.  The section is terminated
			with an ASCII NUL character.

			The boolean flags have one byte for each flag.  This byte is
			either 0 or 1 as the flag is present or absent.  The capabilities
			are in the same order as the file term.h.

			Between the boolean section and the number section, a null byte
			will be inserted, if necessary, to ensure that the number section
			begins on an even byte (this is a relic of the PDP-11's
			word-addressed architecture, originally designed in to avoid IOT
			traps induced by addressing a word on an odd byte boundary).
			All short integers are aligned on a short word boundary.

			The numbers section is similar to the flags section.  Each capability
			takes up two bytes, and is stored as a little-endian short integer.
			If the value represented is -1, the capability is taken to be
			missing.

			The strings section is also similar.  Each capability is stored as a
			short integer, in the format above.  A value of -1 means the
			capability is missing.  Otherwise, the value is taken as an offset
			from the beginning of the string table.  Special characters in ^X or
			\c notation are stored in their interpreted form, not the printing
			representation.  Padding information $nn and parameter information
			%x are stored intact in uninterpreted form.

			The final section is the string table.  It contains all the values of
			string capabilities referenced in the string section.  Each string is
			null terminated.

   			EXTENDED STORAGE FORMAT
			The previous section describes the conventional terminfo binary
			format.  With some minor variations of the offsets (see PORTABILITY),
			the same binary format is used in all modern UNIX systems.  Each
			system uses a predefined set of boolean, number or string
			capabilities.

			The ncurses libraries and applications support extended terminfo
			binary format, allowing users to define capabilities which are loaded
			at runtime.  This extension is made possible by using the fact that
			the other implementations stop reading the terminfo data when they
			have reached the end of the size given in the header.  ncurses checks
			the size, and if it exceeds that due to the predefined data,
			continues to parse according to its own scheme.

			First, it reads the extended header (5 short integers):

				(1)  count of extended boolean capabilities

				(2)  count of extended numeric capabilities

				(3)  count of extended string capabilities

				(4)  size of the extended string table in bytes.

				(5)  last offset of the extended string table in bytes.

			Using the counts and sizes, ncurses allocates arrays and reads data
			for the extended capabilities in the same order as the header
			information.

			The extended string table contains values for string capabilities.
			After the end of these values, it contains the names for each of the
			extended capabilities in order, e.g., booleans, then numbers and
			finally strings.
			
			PORTABILITY         
			Note that it is possible for setupterm to expect a different set of
			capabilities than are actually present in the file.  Either the
			database may have been updated since setupterm has been recompiled
			(resulting in extra unrecognized entries in the file) or the program
			may have been recompiled more recently than the database was updated
			(resulting in missing entries).  The routine setupterm must be
			prepared for both possibilities - this is why the numbers and sizes
			are included.  Also, new capabilities must always be added at the end
			of the lists of boolean, number, and string capabilities.

			Despite the consistent use of little-endian for numbers and the
			otherwise self-describing format, it is not wise to count on
			portability of binary terminfo entries between commercial UNIX
			versions.  The problem is that there are at least three versions of
			terminfo (under HP-UX, AIX, and OSF/1) which diverged from System V
			terminfo after SVr1, and have added extension capabilities to the
			string table that (in the binary format) collide with System V and
			XSI Curses extensions.  See terminfo(5) for detailed discussion of
			terminfo source compatibility issues.
		</Description>
		<OtherReferences>
			curses(3X), terminfo(5).
		</OtherReferences>
	</page>
	<!-- Superuser and System Administration Commands - sshd -->
	<page id = "sshd">
		<Type>SuperUser</Type>

		<Name>  sshd </Name>
		<Usage> sshd -- OpenSSH SSH daemon
			sshd	[-46DdeiqTt] [-b bits] [-C connection_spec]
					[-c host_certificate_file] [-E log_file] [-f config_file]
					[-g login_grace_time] [-h host_key_file] [-k key_gen_time]
					[-o option] [-p port] [-u len]

		</Usage>
		<Description> sshd (OpenSSH Daemon) is the daemon program for ssh(1).
			Together these programs replace rlogin and rsh, and provide
			secure encrypted communcations between two untrusted hosts
			over an insecure network.

			sshd listens for connections from clients.  It is normally started at
			boot from /etc/rc.  It forks a new daemon for each incoming
			connection. The forked daemons handle key exchange, encryption,
			authentication, command execution, and data exchange.

			sshd can be configured using command-line options or a
			configuration file (by default sshd_config(5)); command-line
			options override values specified in the configuration file.
			sshd rereads its configuration file when it receives a hangup
			signal, SIGHUP, by executing itself with the name and options
			it was started with, e.g. /usr/sbin/sshd.

			The options are as follows:

			-4      Forces sshd to use IPv4 addresses only.

			-6      Forces sshd to use IPv6 addresses only.

			-b bits
				    Specifies the number of bits in the ephemeral protocol version
				    1 server key (default 1024).

			-C connection_spec
				Specify the connection parameters to use for the -T extended
				test mode.  If provided, any Match directives in the configura‐
				tion file that would apply to the specified user, host, and
				address will be set before the configuration is written to
				standard output.  The connection parameters are supplied as
				keyword=value pairs.  The keywords are “user”, “host”, “laddr”,
				“lport”, and “addr”.  All are required and may be supplied in
				any order, either with multiple -C options or as a comma-sepa‐
				rated list.

			-c host_certificate_file
				Specifies a path to a certificate file to identify sshd during
				key exchange.  The certificate file must match a host key file
				specified using the -h option or the HostKey configuration
				directive.

			-D  When this option is specified, sshd will not detach and does
				not become a daemon.  This allows easy monitoring of sshd.

			-d  Debug mode.  The server sends verbose debug output to
				standard error, and does not put itself in the background.
				The server also will not fork and will only process one
				connection. This option is only intended for debugging
				for the server.  Multiple -d options increase the debugging
				level.  Maximum is 3.

			-E log_file
				Append debug logs to log_file instead of the system log.

			-e  Write debug logs to standard error instead of the system log.

			-f config_file
				Specifies the name of the configuration file.  The default is
				/etc/ssh/sshd_config.  sshd refuses to start if there is no
				configuration file.

			-g login_grace_time
				Gives the grace time for clients to authenticate themselves
				(default 120 seconds).  If the client fails to authenticate the
				user within this many seconds, the server disconnects and
				exits.  A value of zero indicates no limit.

			-h host_key_file
				Specifies a file from which a host key is read.  This option
				must be given if sshd is not run as root (as the normal host
				key files are normally not readable by anyone but root).  The
				default is /etc/ssh/ssh_host_key for protocol version 1, and
				/etc/ssh/ssh_host_dsa_key, /etc/ssh/ssh_host_ecdsa_key.
				/etc/ssh/ssh_host_ed25519_key and /etc/ssh/ssh_host_rsa_key
				for protocol version 2.  It is possible to have multiple host
				key files for the different protocol versions and host key
				algorithms.

			-i  Specifies that sshd is being run from inetd(8).  If SSH proto‐
				col 1 is enabled, sshd should not  normally be run from inetd
				because it needs to generate the server key before it can
				respond to the client, and this may take some time.  Clients
				may have to wait too long if the key was regenerated every
				time.

			-k key_gen_time
				Specifies how often the ephemeral protocol version 1 server key
				is regenerated (default 3600 seconds, or one hour).  The moti‐
				vation for regenerating the key fairly often is that the key is
				not stored anywhere, and after about an hour it becomes impos‐
				sible to recover the key for decrypting intercepted communica‐
				tions even if the machine is cracked into or physically seized.
				A value of zero indicates that the key will never be regener‐
				ated.

			-o option
				Can be used to give options in the format used in the configu‐
				ration file.  This is useful for specifying options for which
				there is no separate command-line flag.  For full details of
				the options, and their values, see sshd_config(5).

			-p port
				Specifies the port on which the server listens for connections
				(default 22).  Multiple port options are permitted.  Ports
				specified in the configuration file with the Port option are
				ignored when a command-line port is specified.  Ports specified
				using the ListenAddress option override command-line ports.

			-q  Quiet mode.  Nothing is sent to the system log.  Normally the
				beginning, authentication, and termination of each connection
				is logged.

			-T  Extended test mode.  Check the validity of the configuration
				file, output the effective configuration to stdout and then
				exit.  Optionally, Match rules may be applied by specifying the
				connection parameters using one or more -C options.

			-t  Test mode.  Only check the validity of the configuration file
				and sanity of the keys.  This is useful for updating sshd reli‐
				ably as configuration options may change.

			-u len  
				This option is used to specify the size of the field in the
				utmp structure that holds the remote host name.  If the
				resolved host name is longer than len, the dotted decimal value
				will be used instead.  This allows hosts with very long host
				names that overflow this field to still be uniquely identified.
				Specifying -u0 indicates that only dotted decimal addresses
				should be put into the utmp file.  -u0 may also be used to pre‐
				vent sshd from making DNS requests unless the authentication
				mechanism or configuration requires it.  Authentication mecha‐
				nisms that may require DNS include RhostsRSAAuthentication,
				HostbasedAuthentication, and using a from="pattern-list" option
				in a key file.  Configuration options that require DNS include
				using a USER@HOST pattern in AllowUsers or DenyUsers.
		</Description>
		<OtherReferences> scp(1), sftp(1), ssh(1), ssh-add(1), ssh-agent(1), ssh-keygen(1),
     		ssh-keyscan(1), chroot(2), login.conf(5), moduli(5), sshd_config(5),
     		inetd(8), sftp-server(8)

		</OtherReferences>
	</page>

</LinuxManPage>

